<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<quiz>
<question id="62171">
        <parent>0</parent>
        <name>43.2.06 Comments on interpretation</name>
        <questiontext>&lt;h3&gt;Comments on interpretation&lt;/h3&gt;

Some care should always be taken when interpreting results obtained from correlation coefficient
calculations.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
(a) A high correlation does not necessarily imply that a causal relationship exists between
the variables considered. For example, it may be that a high degree of correlation exists
between the number of road accidents in a particular city and the number of late trains
arriving at a station in another city both over the same time period. In general one would
not expect to find a causal relation between the variables involved. Similar comments
apply to, for example, water hardness and average income for towns in the UK.

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
(b) When considering the behaviour of two variables, one should realize that it is possible
that both variables may change because of the influence of a third variable. An example
often quoted in this context is the Gas law
\[\dfrac{PV}{T} = \text{constant} \]
where say, pressure and volume may change because of a change in temperature.

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
(c) A low value of the correlation coefficient does not necessarily imply that no relationship
exists between the variables being considered. Remember that the correlation coefficient 
is indicative of a &lt;i&gt;linear relationship only&lt;/i&gt; and that a low or zero value of \(r\) may indicate
that a non-linear relationship exists. For example a set of points lying on the curve \(y = x^2\)&lt;i&gt;
might&lt;/i&gt; result in a zero value of \(r\).</questiontext>
        <questiontextformat>1</questiontextformat>
        <generalfeedback/>
        <generalfeedbackformat>1</generalfeedbackformat>
        <defaultmark>0.0000000</defaultmark>
        <penalty>0.0000000</penalty>
        <qtype>description</qtype>
        <length>0</length>
        <stamp>stack2.maths.ed.ac.uk+200707193307+ZdwSVe</stamp>
        <version>stack2.maths.ed.ac.uk+200708183850+VOWDNY</version>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timecreated>1594150387</timecreated>
        <timemodified>1594233530</timemodified>
        <createdby>642</createdby>
        <modifiedby>642</modifiedby>
        <idnumber>$@NULL@$</idnumber>
        <question_hints>
        </question_hints>
        <tags>
        </tags>
      </question>
      

</quiz>